<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true tryall of the ministers and ministry of England; as also a true discovery of their root and foundation, and of the called English Church, with its honours, possessions, tythes, and maintenance. Together with the fruits of the said ministers and ministry. Published for the sake of the simple ones, that they may no longer be deceived; but may come to witnesse the altar, whereof they have no right to eat who serve at the tabernacle, Hebr. 13. 10. / Written forth by Gervase Benson.</title>
            <author>Benson, Gervase, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E857_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206612</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865731</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76406)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E857[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true tryall of the ministers and ministry of England; as also a true discovery of their root and foundation, and of the called English Church, with its honours, possessions, tythes, and maintenance. Together with the fruits of the said ministers and ministry. Published for the sake of the simple ones, that they may no longer be deceived; but may come to witnesse the altar, whereof they have no right to eat who serve at the tabernacle, Hebr. 13. 10. / Written forth by Gervase Benson.</title>
                  <author>Benson, Gervase, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, at the Black-Spread-Eagle, near the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob. 27. 1655".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  History --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117980:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A True Tryall of the Miniſters and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of England; As alſo a true Diſcovery of their Root and Foundation, and of the called <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, with its Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Poſſeſsions, Tythes and Maintenance. Together with the fruits of the ſaid Miniſters and Miniſtry.</head>
            <head type="sub">Publiſhed for the ſake of the ſimple Ones, that they may no longer be deceived; but may come to witneſſe the Altar, whereof they have no right to eat who ſerve the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.10.</head>
            <byline>Written forth by <hi>Gervaſe Benſon.</hi>
            </byline>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>The Heathen are ſunk down in the pit that they made: in the net which they hid is their own foot taken,</p>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 9.15.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>His miſchief ſhall return upon his own head; and his violent dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhall come upon his own pate,</p>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 7.16.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FRiends and People: Now in your dayes is the Lord, who is the Living and Faithfull God, fulfilling his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? and hath fulfilled what he ſaid by <hi>Iſaias</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.9. <hi>The people that walked in darkneſs have ſeen a great light; and they that dwelt in the Land of the ſhadow of death, upon them hath the light ſhined.</hi> By which their feet are guided into the way of peace: and in which light they ſee their ſalvation, through the tender mercy of God, and the remiſſion of their ſins, through the knowledge of Him, who is <hi>the Light of the world,</hi> and hath <hi>enlightened every one that cometh into the world:</hi> which light is the Saints Teacher; and the Worlds Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation that hate it. Therefore that all of you might come to know the true God, whom ye ignorantly worſhip,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117980:2"/>(both Prieſts and People) who contrary to the light do walk, and act; To the light which Chriſt Jeſus hath enlightened you withall, take heed, and it love, and obey, in whatſoever it ſhall ſhew unto you; (That is the light which ſhewes you darkneſſe, ſin, and evill, and all things that ever you have done, brings to remembrance;) and all your Deeds, to the Light bring, that with it they may be proved, whether, or nay, they be wrought in God: for all things that are repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved are made manifeſt by the light, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.13. And that with the light ye may come to ſee Him, who is the way to the <hi>Father of Lights, with whom is no variableneſſe, nor ſhadow of change;</hi> who is the Truth: And there is no coming to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by Him, who is the Life, who is the beloved Son of God; in whom alone he is well pleaſed; who the true Prophet is, which God promiſed he would raiſe up, whom all the people ſhould hear, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22, 23. and every Soul that will not hear this Prophet (whom God hath raiſed up for a <hi>light to the Gentiles, that he might be his ſalvation unto the ends of the earth,</hi> Iſa. 49.6.) ſhall be deſtroyed from among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſalvation they ſhall never witneſſe; <hi>for there is no other Name under heaven given among men whereby they muſt be ſaved;</hi> neither is there ſalvation in any other, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. but by this Jeſus, who continueth a Prieſt for ever, over the houſhold of God, who to himſelf took not this honour, but <hi>he that ſaid unto him, Thou art my Son, this day begat I thee, he alſo ſaith, Thou art a Prieſt for ever, after the order of Melchize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deek,</hi> who endureth for ever, hath an everlaſting Prieſthood, who perfectly ſaveth them that come to God by him: who is holy, harmleſſe, undefiled, and ſeparate from ſinners, who is conſecrated for evermore, ever liveth to make interceſſion for the Saints; who is become their High Prieſt of good things to come, by a greater and more perfect Tabernacle, not made with hands: That is to ſay, not of this building; who by his own blood entred in once, into the holy place, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117980:2"/>obtained eternall redemption for them whoſe conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences he hath, and doth purge from dead works, to ſerve the living God; not in the oldneſſe of the letter, but in the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. Whoſe hearts are ſprinkled from an evil conſcience, and their bodies waſhed with pure water.</p>
            <p>And of this Saviour Jeſus, and this High Preiſt, whom God hath exalted, and is exalting with his Right Hand, to be a Prince, and a Saviour; are they witneſſes who have belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Light, who are the Children of the Light, who by the Children of Darkneſſe (which hate the light, whoſe words and deeds be evill) are in deriſion called Quakers: who witneſſe Him in them, who is greater then he that is in the world; who is entred into the Holieſt of all, daily ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king interceſſion for them. And the true Tabernacle made without hands, they are witneſſes of: and the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the anointing, that teacheth them of all things, ſo that they need not, that any man teach them: but as the ſame anointing teacheth them, of all things and is true, and is no lye. And by the Holy Ghoſt, which he hath given them, can they truly ſay; That Jeſus is the Lord, and that in him, they are compleat, which is the head of all Principality and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, in whom alſo they are Circumciſed, with the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fion made without hands, in putting off the body of the ſins of the fleſh, by the circumciſion of Chriſt, buried with him in Baptiſme; wherein alſo they are riſen with him, through the faith of the operation of God, who hath raiſed him from the dead, who is the firſt and the laſt: Even he that liveth and was dead, and behold he liveth for evermore. And with the light which from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt doth come they do ſee and know, That other Lords and Prieſts, beſides him have had Dominion over them, but he that hath wrought, and doth work all their works in them; the living powerfull God of Life and Light, hath made and is making,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117980:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>their memory to periſh: who have brought nothing to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, who hold up thoſe places wherein the Nations ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their gods, which the Lord commanded ſhould utterly be deſtroyed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.2. And do allow, and practiſe thoſe things which then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> diſanulled, blotted out, and nailed to the Croſſe, the hand-writing of Ordinances, impoſed untill the time of reformation: Of which time and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the People of God called Quakers are witneſſes in life, and power: and ſo alſo is the Holy Ghoſt. And the time is accompliſhed, wherein the Lord is drawn near to judgment, and is become a ſwift witneſſe, againſt the Sorcerers, and againſt the Adulterers, and againſt the Oppreſſors, and againſt the Hirelings: And againſt the Shepheards, that feed themſelves with the fat, and cloath themſelves with the wooll; but feed not the flock: And againſt the Scoffers, and againſt all who after their own ungodly luſts walk; who are talkers of a reformation; but ſay that the time is not yet come. Men of corrupt minds they are, being deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of the Truth, ſuppoſing that gain is godlineſſe: who go about to uphold a worldly Sanctuary, and make Prieſts of the loweſt of the people, which are not the Sons of <hi>Levi:</hi> who ſet up a worſhip, deviſed of their own heart; for which they have neither precept nor example, in the Scriptures: and take Tythes of the People, and demand them as theirs by a humane Law, made in the will of Man; which the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt Jeſus never did act any ſuch thing, nor ſue any man at the law: but he that preached the Goſpel, liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Goſpel; for ſo hath the Lord ordained. Neither did <hi>Levi,</hi> nor his Sons under the firſt Prieſthood act any ſuch thing; for that Prieſthood was made by a law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.13, 14. and <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.1. And had a commandement to take Tythes of the people according to the Law, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.5. And no man took this honour to himſelf, but he that was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was, <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 5.4. And thoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117980:3"/>that did not bring their Tythes to the Store-houſe robbed God, <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.8, 10. and not the Prieſts, neither were the Prieſts to go to the Magiſtrate to compell them by a law, to pay them Tythes, and Treble damages (as the Prieſts now in <hi>England</hi> do) but according to all that the Lord command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo did they: as you may read, <hi>Levit.</hi> 8.36. But theſe men now in England, who are called Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and of Chriſt, are neither called of God (who never heard his voice) as <hi>Aaron</hi> was, and thoſe under the firſt priſthood: who received their Law from God, and had a commandement from Him to take Tythes of the People; Nor as the Miniſters of the Goſpel were called, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed their call from God, not of men, neither by man; but by Jeſus Chriſt and God the Father, who raiſed him from the dead, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. And the Goſpell which was preached by them was not after man, neither received they it of man: neither was taught it but by Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt. And Chriſt-Jeſus is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever, and the Goſpell is the ſame, for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. If any preach another Goſpell, then that which we have preached, let him be accurſed. And the Miniſters of Chriſt are the ſame, and are one, who hold one Head, who are led and guided by one ſpirit, even the Spirit of Truth, which the world cannot receive, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.17. And as many as are led by the Spirit of Chriſt, they are the Miniſters of Chriſt, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in his Doctrine, and do whatſoever he commandeth them; But they that have not the Spirit of Chriſt, (even the ſame ſpirit which was in the Apoſtles of Chriſt) they are none of his Miniſters, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. And they that deny Revelation, and affirm and ſay, That all Revelation is ceaſed, are no Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, who know not the Father, nor the Son, <hi>For no man knoweth the Father but by the Son, and he to whomſoever the Son will reveal him,</hi> Matth. 11.27. And they who were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117980:4"/>the Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus witneſſed Revelations, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered and preached to others, no other doctrine, but what they received of the Lord. Even that which from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was, which they had heard, which they had ſeen with their Eyes: which they had looked upon, and their hands had handled of the Word of Life, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3. which Word of Life, thoſe called Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> who deny Revelation, who ſue men at the law for Tythes and maintenance, never heard; who are yet in their ſins, who live in pride, covetouſneſſe, and oppreſſion; who hold, and teach that none can be free from ſin, nor overcome ſin, whileſt they live here, contrary to plain Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.18.22. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.13, 14. And ſo they being ſervants of ſin, are free from righteouſneſſe: for it is they that are free from ſin, that are the Miniſters of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.18. For he that commits ſin is the ſervant of ſin: and no man can ſerve two Maſters: none can be the Servant of Chriſt, whileſt he is the ſervant of ſin, <hi>John</hi> 8.34. For Chriſt and ſin, are two contrary Maſters: and betwixt light and darkneſſe there is no fellowſhip, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. For whoſoever finneth hath not ſeen Chriſt neither known him, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.6. And how can they be Chriſt Miniſters, who neither knew him nor ever ſaw him? For who are Chriſts Miniſters, he is their Lord and Maſter, and they do whatſoever he commandeth them, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 13.13. And where Chriſt Jeſus is made manifeſt the works of the Devill are deſtroyed, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.8. Now ſin is of the Devill, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.7, 8. And the Devill is no Miniſter of Chriſt, nor none that are of him: and he that commits ſin is of the devill, who was a lyar from the beginning and abode not in the truth, becauſe there is no truth in him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.44. neither is there truth in them: who teach for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines the Tradition of men, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.9. Who hold up a worſhip and maintenance, and the high places deviſed by man: which they received by Tradition from the Pope, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117980:4"/>his Prelates, after the cuſtomes of the Nations, and not after Chriſt, who make the Commandements of God of none ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by their traditions: theſe are ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpoke of, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.2. who give heed to ſeducing ſpirits, and doctrines of devills, ſpeaking lies in hypocriſie, having their conſciences ſeared with a hot Iron: who run but God never ſent them; and ſay, Thus ſaith the Lord, when he never ſpoke to them: and therefore it is, they have not profited the people at all; becauſe they ſtood not in the counſel of the moſt High God, who are not built upon the foundation of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, and Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, the Rock of ages: but from the foundation of the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Diſciples of Chriſt Jeſus, they are razed and excluded, who are unholy; for if their Root had been holy, the branches would have been holy alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. but their fruits have made them manifeſt, to have ſprung up from the bitter root: who have troubled and defiled many, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.15. them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being unclean, manifeſting their root. And therefore all people, every where, conſider what ye are doing, that hold up a Generation of men, whom you call Miniſters of Chriſt, and of the Goſpel, who be unholy, and uncleane, who do the Temple of God defile: who in the way of <hi>Cain</hi> do go; and after the Errour of <hi>Balaam</hi> for rewards run gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily: Theſe are they that be ſpots in your feaſts of Charity, when they feaſt with you, they feed themſelves without fear; clouds they are without water, carried about of winds; Trees, whoſe fruit withereth, without fruit; who are Murmurers and Complainers, who can never have enough, who ſay, What ſhall we eat? what ſhall we drink? wherewithall ſhall we be cloathed? <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.25, &amp;c. Heathens they are, and no Miniſters of Chriſt; who after their own ungodly luſts do walk, whoſe mouthes ſpeak great ſwelling words, having men perſons in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117980:5"/>for advantage, ſenſuall they are, who have not the ſame ſpirit, which was in the Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt, as ſundry of them have confeſſed and publiſhed in print: whoſe Foundation and Root is now diſcovered and made manifeſt; whom ye call your Miniſters, Parſons, Vicars, and Curats: and the foundation of your Churches, as you call them, and your Pariſhes, and your Fonts, and your Baſons, and your Sacraments, for which there is no Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; and your Infants Baptiſme, and your Tythes Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall, and Parſonall; and your Oblations, Obventions, and Eaſter Reckonings, and Mortuaries; and your Cryſoms, and your Churching of Women, and your firſt-fruits, and your Patrons, and your Preſentations, and your Orders, and your Approbations, and Augmentations; and all your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as you call it, which is not <hi>in Spirit, and in truth,</hi> to be of man, and from man, and was invented by fallen man: and their Titles and Dignities they received of man, and from man, and one from another; and their Original Head, and Root, and Foundation, was the Archbiſhops and Biſhops (amongſt which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> called the Pope, was Chief, and Supream head) untill the Raign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, late King of <hi>England,</hi> as by the Lawes and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this Nation doth and may appear. And theſe called Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and ſuch as received Orders from them to be Prieſts, Miniſters and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and Clerks as they called them; were called the body Spiritual, and were and are called the Engliſh-Church, as by the Statute of 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Cap. 12. doth and may appear. And as that Statute declareth; The Kings and Nobles of this Realm, endowed the ſaid Church both with honour and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, to keep them from corruption and ſiniſter affection. And the Pope and the See of <hi>Rome</hi> had the Tryal (amongſt other things) of the right of Tythes, Oblations and Obven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117980:5"/>And by that Statute it is ordained and declared, That all ſpiritual Prelates, Paſtors, Miniſters and Curates within the Realm of <hi>England</hi> may uſe, Miniſter, execute, and do all Sacraments and Sacramentalls, and Divine Service unto the Subjects of the ſame: And by the Statute of the 26. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Chap. 1. King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and his Succeſſours is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the onely Supream Head in earth of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland:</hi> And by the Statute of the 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Chap. 20. The Annals or firſt fruits which were payed by the Archbiſhops and Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> are taken from the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> called the Pope: And by the Statute of the 26. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Chap. 3. The firſt fruits and profits of every Archbiſhoprick and Biſhoprick, Parſonage, Vicaridge, &amp;c. are given to <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and his Succeſſours; and over and beſides a yearly tenth of all ſpiritual livings, as they are called. And by the Statute of the 25. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Chap. 20. It is ordained and eſtabliſhed, That the King and his Succeſſours may grant to the Prior and Covent, or the Dean and Chapter of the Cathedral Churches or Monaſteries a Licence under the great Seal, as of old time hath been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, to proceed to the Election of an Archbiſhop or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, at every avoidance of any Archbiſhoprick or Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick within the Realm of <hi>England:</hi> with a Letter Miſſive con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the name of the perſon which they ſhall Elect, and chooſe, &amp;c. And by the Statute of the 25. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Chap. 21. The Archbiſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> have Power and Authority given at their diſcretions to grant Diſpenſations, Licences, &amp;c. unto the King, his Heires and Succeſſours, for cauſes not being contrary to the holy Scriptures; as before had been accuſtomed and uſed to be obtained by the Kings of <hi>England</hi> from the See of <hi>Rome.</hi> And by a Statute made 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Chap. 12. It is ordained, that every perſon under the degree of a Biſhop, which doth or ſhall pretend to be a Prieſt or a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117980:6"/>Miniſter of Gods holy Word and Sacraments, &amp;c. ſhall in the preſence of the Biſhop declare his aſſent, and ſubſcribe to all the Articles of Religion, which concern the confeſſion of the true Chriſtian faith, and the doctrine of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments comprized in a Book imprinted, Entituled <hi>Articles</hi> whereupon it was agreed by the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, and the whole Clergie in the Convocation holden at <hi>London</hi> in the year, 1562. And that none ſhould be made Miniſter, or admitted to preach, or adminiſter the Sacraments in <hi>England</hi> under the age of 24 years: or unleſſe he be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, being a Deacon at the leaſt, &amp;c. And all admiſſions to Benefices, &amp;c. and all Licences or Tolerations made to the contrary to be meerly void in Law, as if they never were. So that it is manifeſt, That the foundation of the late Archbiſhops and Biſhops here in <hi>England</hi> was Man, <hi>viz.</hi> The Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> with the Priors and Covent of Monaſteries, and the Deanes and Chapiters of the Cathedrals. And that the Miniſters, Parſons, Preachers, Vicars, and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats, as they call them, were members and branches, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from that Root and Body; To wit, The Archbiſhops and Biſhops; which Archbiſhops and Biſhops by a late Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament were and are aboliſhed and taken away. And by another Ordinance or Act of Parliament, the Kingly Power and Government was and is taken away and rendred uſeleſſe in this Nation: and the ſame declared to be a free Common-Wealth. And by another Ordinance of Parliament the late Deans and Chapiters, &amp;c. are alſo aboliſhed and taken away: So that it is manifeſt by the Lawes, Statutes, and Ordinances aforeſaid; That the called Prieſts, Miniſters, Rectors, Parſons, Preachers, Vicars, and Curats, were Members and Branches of the late Archbiſhops and Biſhops of this Nation; and had their riſing, and ſprung
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117980:6"/>from that Root and Body, and of that Root and Body were members and branches: And that the Archbiſhops and Biſhops themſelves were made and had their riſe from the late Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> with the Priors and Covents, and Dean and Chapiters aforeſaid: which ſaid Kings and Queens, Priors, Covents, Monaſteries, Deans and Chapiters, Archbiſhops and Biſhops, Root and Branch, and their Power and Authorities, being diſannulled, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and declared uſeleſſe, aboliſhed, and taken away as aforeſaid: It doth clearly appear, and is manifeſt; That all the Prieſts ſo called, and Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> with the called Rectors, Parſons, Preachers, Vicars, Clerks, and Curats, being Branches and Members of that Root and Body, <hi>viz.</hi> the late Archbiſhops and Biſhops, as branches and members of that Body and Root, are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, diſannulled, and aboliſhed; and the Root of their Root, the Kings and Queens of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. And thus having clearly proved, and made manifeſt their foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to be of man, and from man: and them and their foundation, and the Root of their Root, by man razed, taken away, made Null, and rendred uſeleſſe; I leave them in the Pit, without foundation, either of God or man, where they and their memory ſhall rot, who have brought nothing to perfection; and all that go about to ſet up, write again, and uphold that which God hath caſt down and diſannulled; and blotted out the hand-writing of Ordinances; the Commandement by which the Prieſts took Tythes, and changed the Prieſthood that was change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that had a Commandement to take Tythes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, during the firſt Prieſthood, as you may read <hi>Hebrews</hi> the 7. And do witneſſe Chriſt Jeſus the unchangeable Prieſthood, the end of all Types, Figures, and changeable things: and the Prieſthood that had a Commandement to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117980:7"/>take Tythes, changed; and the Law by which they took Tythes, diſannulled: becauſe of the weakneſſe and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitableneſſe thereof; for the Law made nothing perfect: but the bringing in of a better hope made perfect, whereby we draw near to God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.18, 19. And do own and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Miniſtery and Miniſters of the Goſpel which is not of man, neither by man, whoſe foundation ſtandeth ſure, abideth for ever, changeth not, neither can be ſhaken; who are built upon the foundation of the Prophets and Apoſtles, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being their chief and head, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. who by him are gifted, for the gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtery, and for the edification of the Body of Chriſt, till they all meet together in the unity of the Faith, and knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man; and unto the meaſure of the age of the fulneſſe of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12, 13. And all who are Miniſters of Chriſt have received a perfect Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, which freely they have received, and freely they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, without being burthenſome to any: And do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and own the Church whereof Chriſt Jeſus is the head, which is his body, which is holy; and the aſſembly of the righteous, from which all the ungodly are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.5. And the Ordinances of Chriſt Jeſus; of which none that are unholy can partake. And do own and witneſſe the worſhip of God, which is <hi>in Spirit and truth:</hi> and the Law of God, <hi>which is holy, juſt, and good,</hi> which never changes by no diverſity of place or time: And do witneſſe, That all Lawes, Statutes, Ordinances, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, or Cuſtomes, brought in againſt this Law writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the heart (which is the Law of the Eternall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable God, though called by many the Law of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or of Nature) to be things void, and againſt Juſtice: and being but the Lawes of men, they are inferiour to the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117980:7"/>Law of God which is Superiour; and therefore to it muſt they give place. And being that Tythes by the Lawes and Statutes of this Nation are given to God, and holy Church. And being as before is proved, That by God, and the Church which is holy, Tythes are denyed: and that the called Church of <hi>England,</hi> the body ſpirituall, called the Spirituality, who receive Tythes, are unholy, not being free from corruption and ſiniſter affection; but ſtand in need of honours and poſſeſſions to keep them from corruption and ſiniſter affection; for which end they were given them, as by the Statute of the 24. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. Chap. 12. it appeareth: Therefore by the Lawes and Statutes of <hi>England,</hi> the called Prieſts, Miniſters, Preachers, Rectors, Parſons, Vicars, Clerks, and Curats, who are unholy, have no right to Tythes; and an Evill cuſtome or uſuage is to be aboliſhed and taken away, ſaith <hi>Cook</hi> upon <hi>Littleton.</hi> And that cuſtome or uſuage which requires me to give wages to him that never did, nor doth any work for me, or mine, is againſt reaſon, which is ſaid to be the ground of all Lawes. And being as afore is ſaid, That all Lawes, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, Cuſtomes, or Preſcriptions againſt the Law written in the heart, called the Law of Reaſon, or the Law of Nature are void: and if any be brought in againſt it, they be no Preſcriptions, Statutes, nor Cuſtomes, but things void, and againſt Juſtice, as you may read in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Student, Chap. 2. Therefore all Lawes, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, Cuſtomes, Uſuages or Preſcriptions, which would ſet up, and uphold that which God hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annulled and made void, and his Law beares witneſſe againſt, and would have me to contribute towards the upholding of a Miniſtery which is changeable, and makes nothing perfect (who are not one amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: neither the ſame this generation, that was the laſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117980:8"/>before; but alters and changes with times and men: as the called Miniſters, and Prieſts of <hi>England,</hi> and their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors have done, as is manifeſt: that in the time of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the eight the late King of <hi>England,</hi> their predeceſſors de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Pope for their head, and owned <hi>Henry</hi> the eight for their head: and in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt, their Predeceſſors denied the Maſſe Book, and received the book of Common praier at his command: And again in Queen <hi>Mary</hi> her time, they denied the Common Prayer Book, and received the Maſſe: And in the time of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> they denied the maſſe Book, and again received the Book of Common prayer: And in the time of the late Parliament they denied the Common Praier Book: and received the Directory, rather then they would deny their Honours and poſſeſſions: and what they now own, is manifeſt to all the the Children of Light; to me they are of no force, nor of me can take hold being thereunto dead: and therefore from them freed, being to another married, even the man Chriſt Jeſus: who is raiſed from the dead, that I ſhould now bring forth fruits to God: and from henceforth ſerve Him in newneſſe of life, and not in the oldneſſe of the Letter, and in ſo doing, by God, and that of God in every mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience I am juſtified: who art thou oh man that condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt? Gods enemy thou art, who contrary to that of God in thy conſcience doth act. And thus to all both Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Prieſts and people have I cleared my conſcience, and laid down the grounds and reaſons why I, who of the world and to the world am known by the name of <hi>Gervaſe Benſon,</hi> deny the called Miniſters and Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> aforeſaid: and to pay Tyths contrary to the Law of God: which is written in my heart not with Ink, but with the Spirit of the living God, who am the ſervant of the living God, who doth him obey: whoſe ſoul is made ſubject to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117980:8"/>the higher powers for conſcience ſake, and to every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be unto the King as unto the Superiour, or unto Governours as unto them that are ſent by him for the puniſhment of evill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and for the prayſe of them that do well, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.14, For ſo is the Will of God that by well doing I may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men; who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſters are of the power which is the Ordinance of God which whoſoever doth reſiſt, ſhall receive to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves damnation: for Rulers are not a terrour to good works but to the evill, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2, 3. And if for my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the Higher Powers, for conſcience ſake: and for bearing witneſſe againſt all reſiſters of the power accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Ordinance of God: or for not ſwearing, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the commands of Chriſt Jeſus, who ſaith, Swear not at all, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. And the doctrine of the Apoſtle of Chriſt, <hi>James</hi> 5.12. who ſaith: <hi>Above all things, my Brethren, ſwear not: neither by Heaven, neither by the Earth, neither by any other oath, but let your yea be yea and your nay nay, leaſt ye fall into condemnation:</hi> or for not putting forth my hand to Act that, which that of God in my conſcience doth ſhew me to be evil: or for not owning a form which is contrary to the Truth: and ſo more then yea and nay, I ſuffer, I ſuffer: knowing (if the Will of God be ſo) It is better to ſuffer for well doing then for evill. And ſo to the Will of my God, I commit my ſoul and body in well-doing, who ſaith, <hi>If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall raign with him: And before Governours and Kings ye ſhall be brought for my ſake, for a Teſtimony againſt them and the Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle,</hi> near the Weſt End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
